MATTIA CAMPANA

Curriculum Vitae



ABOUT ME

I am Mattia Campana, I was born on 7th April 1987 in Milano (Italy). I received a Ph.D. in Computer Engineering at the University of Pisa in collaboration with the Institute for Informatics and Telematics of the National Research Council of Italy (IIT-CNR).

Currently, I am a Researcher and member of the ubiquitous Internet Research Unit at the IIT-CNR. My research interests are in the field of Future Internet, mainly working on Contextaware Recommender Systems, mobile middleware solutions and algorithms to automatically recognise the user's context and social relationships in mobile environment.

CONTACTS

Mattia Campana

Via Fratelli Antoni, 1 56121 Pisa (Italy)

campana.mattia@gmail.com

+39 339 345 7653









EDUCATION

UNIVERSITY OF PISA & IIT-CNR, 2016 - 2019

Ph.D. in Computer Engineering at the University of Pisa (Italy), in collaboration with the Institute for Informatics and Telematics of the National Research Council of Italy (IIT-CNR). The title of my thesis is "Context-Aware Recommender Systems for Opportunistic Environments" (English only).

UNIVERSITY OF MILANO, 2015

MS.c in Computer Science. Title of the thesis: "Context reasoning algorithms for mobile devices" (Italian only).

UNIVERSITY OF MILANO, 2011

BS.C. in Computer Science. Title of the thesis: "Security analysis of the Android operating system". (Italian only).

WORK EXPERIENCES

RESEARCH SCIENTIST, IIT-CNR, AUG 2020 - NOW

Member of the Ubiquitous Internet Research Unit of the Institute for Informatics and Telematics of the National Research Council of Italy (IIT-CNR).

RESEARCH FELLOW, IIT-CNR, JUN 2015 - JUL 2020

Design and evaluation of Pervasive Context-aware Recommender Systems and context recognition algorithms.

RESEARCH ASSISTANT, IIT-CNR, JUL 2014 - FEB 2015

Design and evaluation of context reasoning algorithms for mobile devices.

FREELANCE MOBILE DEVELOPER, 2013 - 2016

Full-stack mobile developer, including the design and development of mobile applications backends (DBMS and RESTful web services), Android and iOS clients.

INTERNSHIPS & SUMMER SCHOOLS

STUDENT VISITOR, HONG KONG, JUN-AUG 2018

During the summer of 2018 I was visiting the System and Media Laboratory at the Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (Hong Kong) to work with Dr. Dimitris Chatzopoulos and Prof. Pan Hui, Nokia Chair in Data Science and Professor of Computer Science at the University of Helsinki [ref].

SUMMER SCHOOL, BOZEN-BOLZANO, AUG 2017

I attended the ACM SIGCHI Summer School on Recommender Systems organised and hosted by the Faculty of Computer Science of the Free University of Bozen-Bolzano (Italy) [ref].

TEACHING EXPERIENCES

TUTOR, MAR - APR 2018

I have tutored 35 high-school students involved in a training period at IIT-CNR, giving them an introduction about both Android development and mobile sensors Data Analysis [ref].



RESEARCH INTERESTS



Self-forming networks for the edge of the Internet and mobile devices.



MACHINE LEARNING AND RECOMMENDER SYSTEMS

Context recognition based on smartphone sensors and user's preferences modelling to provide personalized services to the user.



MOBILE SOCIAL NETWORKS

Modelling the user social relationships to optimize data the dissemination among mobile devices.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages

Java	•	•	•	•	•
Python	•	•	•	•	•
Objective-C	•	•	•	•	•

Databases

MySQL	•	•	•	•	
PostgreSQL	•	•	•	•	•
PostGIS	•	•	•	•	•
MongoDB	•	•	•	•	•

Data Science Frameworks/Tools

Pandas	•	•	•	•	•
Numpy	•	•	•	•	•
SciPy	•	•	•	•	•
Jupyter	•	•	•	•	
R	•	•	•	•	•

Machine Learning Frameworks

Scikit-Learn	•	•	•	•	
Keras	•	•	•	•	•

Developing Frameworks/Tools

Jersey	•	•	•	•	•
Flask	•	•	•		
Apache Maven	•	•	•	•	•
Git	•	•	•	•	•
Android Studio	•	•	•	•	•
Xcode	•	•	•	•	•

RESEARCH PROJECTS

Since 2015 I am involved in the following research projects [ref]:

- Mobilitando Pisa (Tuscany Region)
- SocializeMe (IIT-CNR)
- INTESA Project (Tuscany Region)
- CAPP (IIT-CNR)

• GAMEBUS (EU Project)

ACADEMIC SERVICES

Technical Program Committee member of PerCrowd 2019 [ref]

Reviewer for:

- IFIP Networking 2018 (Conference) [ref]
- Online Social Network and Media (Journal, Elsevier) [ref]
- Symmetry (Journal, MDPI)
- Journal of Ambient Intelligence and Humanized Computing (Journal, Springer)

Publicity Chair of IFIP IoP-W 2016 [ref]

PUBLICATIONS

INTERNATIONAL SCIENTIFIC JOURNALS

- M. Campana, F. Delmastro. **MyDigitalFootprint:** an extensive context dataset for pervasive computing applications at the edge. Pervasive and Mobile Computing, Elsevier, 2020 [Under review, minor revision]
- M. Campana, F. Delmastro. **COMPASS: Unsupervised and Online Clustering of Human Complex Activities from Smartphone Sensors**. Expert Systems with Applications, Elsevier, 2020 [Under review]
- M. Campana, F. Delmastro. **ContextLabeler Dataset: physical and virtual sensors data collected from smartphones usage in-the-wild**. Data in brief, Elsevier, 2020 [Under review]
- M. Campana, F. Delmastro. Recommender Systems for Online and Mobile Social Networks: A survey. Online Social Networks and Media, Elsevier, 2017
- V. Arnaboldi, M. Campana, F. Delmastro, **A personalized recommender system for pervasive social networks**. Pervasive and Mobile Computing, Elsevier, 2017

INTERNATIONAL SCIENTIFIC CONFERENCES

- M. Campana, D. Chatzopoulos, F. Delmastro, P. Hui, **Lightweight Modeling of User Context Combining Physical and Virtual Sensor Data**. ACM UbiComp/ISWC'18 Adjunct, 2018, Singapore.
- V. Arnaboldi, M. Campana, F. Delmastro, Context-Aware Configuration and Management of WiFi Direct Groups for Real Opportunistic Networks. IEEE MASS 2017, Orlando, Florida, USA.
- M. Campana, F. Delmastro, R. Bruno, A machine-learned ranking algorithm for dynamic and personalised car pooling services. IEEE ITSC 2017, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.
- V. Arnaboldi, M. Campana, F. Delmastro, **PLIERS: a popularity-based recommender system for content dissemination in online social networks.** ACM SAC 2016, Pisa, Italy.

MbcCay

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

- Data collection
- Data Analysis
- Experiments design
- · Fast prototyping
- Writing both technical reports and scientific papers
- Technical Presentation

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Italian Native

English C1 [ref] [ref]

PROJECTS

ContextKit, 2018 - NOW [ref]

ContextKit is a mobile framework that provides context-aware features to mobile devices and third-party applications. It is composed of a sensing layer that tracks a broad set of heterogeneous sensors to model different aspects of the user context in the mobile environment, including her mobility patterns, preferences, habits, and social interactions with other people. I am currently working on the extension of ContextKit that includes a reasoning layer that implements different machine learning models (both supervised and unsupervised) to recognise the user's context, based on the data collected by the sensing layer.

GoTogether, 2016 [ref]

A car pooling application in which users can offer their own car to share specific trips or search for rides and become passengers. The app provides recommendations tailored to the user's profile, her preferences, needs and her behaviour while using the application. It has been originally designed for users of the research area of CNR in Pisa in the framework of SMART AREA project.

Developed components: RESTful web-service (Java Jersey), and Android native application.

HughMe App, 2016

A dating application developed for HugMe LLC company.

Developed components: RESTful web-service (Java Jersey), iOS and Android native applications.

Woof, 2013 [ref]

A social network designed for dogs lovers.

Developed components: RESTful web-service (Java Jersey), iOS and Android native applications.

